{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "In 1970, the concluding game of this event featured the dramatic entrance of an injured Willis\nReed. This event included the \"flu game\" in 1997 and an upset in 2011 that put a championship\nin the hands of Jason Terry, Shawn Marion, and Dirk Nowitski. For 10 points, name this annual\nJune event, which awards the Larry O'Brien trophy to teams such as the Bulls, Heat, or Lakers.",
      "answer": "the NBA Finals"
    },
    {
      "question": "A song of this kind derives its melody from \"La Montovana,\" the same folk song that is the\norigin of \"The Moldau\" (pr. MOLE-dow), and is called \"Hatikvah\" (pr. hah-TEEK-vuh).\nSongs of the kind include Jana Gana Mana (pr. jah-NAH guh-nuh MOO-nuh) and La\nMarseillaise (pr. MAHR-see-YEZ). For 10 points, identify this type of song, such as \"God Save\nthe Queen.\"",
      "answer": [
        "national anthems"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Two sports teams based in this country met in the Naismith Cup. In 1993, a team based in this\ncountry employed John Olerud and Paul Molitor. This country's lesser-known national sport is\nlacrosse, and its football league contests the Grey Cup every year. For 10 points, name this\nformer home of the NBA's Grizzlies and current home of baseball's Blue Jays.",
      "answer": "Canada"
    },
    {
      "question": "One of these objects was taken by Vladimir Putin from Robert Kraft, who has earned four of them\nas an owner. The 1972 design symbolically includes 17 diamonds, and their designs often include gems\nand diamonds in the shapes of Roman numerals and the Vince Lombardi trophy. Tom Brady of the New\nEngland Patriots has four of, for ten points, what type of personal jewelry given to players and staff of\nteams who win the NFL championship?",
      "answer": "Super Bowl ring"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man’s death was most likely in revenge of his killing of Jesus Herrera. His defeat at the Battle\nof Celaya by Alvaro Obregon led him to escape to Chihuahua. The assassination of Francesco Madero led\nthis man to form a military band known as the Division of the North. This man’s raid in Columbus led\nan unsuccessful expedition by John Pershing to capture him. For ten points, name this early 20th century\nMexican bandit.",
      "answer": "Pancho Villa"
    },
    {
      "question": "(TIEBREAKER EXAMPLE QUESTION) What sport, played by Lionel Messi and opposing soldiers during the Christmas Truce,\nnames a brief 1969 war between El Salvador and Honduras?",
      "answer": [
        "football",
        "soccer",
        "Football War",
        "Soccer War"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "During one of these campaigns, a king died with his son John Tristan, who had been born in Damietta\nduring a different one of these campaigns. The leader of one of these campaigns, Simon de Montfort, was\nkilled while besieging Toulouse. The Albigensian one of these conflicts defeated the Cathars in the south\nof France, and Louis IX was canonized for his efforts in the seventh and eighth ones of these against Egypt\nand Tunisia. For ten points, name these conflicts, called by the Pope, that targeted religious enemies.",
      "answer": "crusades"
    },
    {
      "question": "A player who won a Super Bowl for this team started his career under a 43-year, $40 million contract\nwith the USFL. That man replaced a quarterback on this team who threw “The Catch” to Dwight Clark\nin the 1982 NFC Championship Game. During the 2016 preseason, this team’s backup quarterback refused\nto stand for the national anthem, beginning a national protest movement. For ten points, name this NFL\nteam whose quarterbacks have included Steve Young, Joe Montana, and Colin Kaepernick.",
      "answer": [
        "San Francisco 49ers",
        "San Francisco",
        "49ers"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "With Johanna Bethune and Isabella Graham, this man’s wife co-founded an organization that is now\nGraham Windham, a youth-focused non-profit; this man’s wife also assisted Dolley Madison with finding\nfunds for the Washington Monument. For ten points, name this husband of Elizabeth Schuyler [skyler],\nan American founding father whose biographer, Ron Chernow, inspired Lin-Manuel Miranda to write a\nBroadway musical.",
      "answer": [
        "Alexander Hamilton",
        "Hamilton"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This action was avoided by Elvis Presley for two months to film King Creole, but his eventual\nperformance of this action inspired the musical Bye Bye Birdie. Muhammad Ali was banned from boxing\nfor 3 years for refusing to engage in this activity. Britain’s Prince Harry started the Invictus Games for\npeople injured in this activity after he did it in Afghanistan. For ten points, name this action which people\nare drafted into through Selective Service.",
      "answer": [
        "military service",
        "conscription",
        "service"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This event was won five straight times by Taiwan before their defeat in 1980 by Kirkland, Washington.\nThe 2014 runner-up in this event was the first all-black team to win the U.S. title, but was retroactively\ndisqualified; that team, representing Jackie Robinson West in Chicago, was ruled to have violated this\nevent’s residency rules. In 2001, the Bronx team finished third in this event with Danny Almonte, who\nwas later found to be 14 years old. For ten points, name this annual international baseball tournament\nheld in South Williamsport, Pennsylvania for 11- to 13-year-olds.",
      "answer": [
        "Little League Baseball World Series",
        "Little League World Series",
        "LLWS"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "A type of music native to this country features the five-string vihuela and the deep-bodied, low-pitched\nguitarron. A folk song with an uneven five-four rhythm about a legless arthropod became popular during\nthis country’s revolution, with lyrics making fun of Victoriano Huerta sung by partisans of Pancho Villa.\nFor ten points, name this country where songs like “La Cucaracha” and “La Bamba” are played by\nmariachi bands south of the United States",
      "answer": [
        "Mexico",
        "United Mexican States",
        "Estados Unidos Mexicanos"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This route was extensively used by the Peoria Party, a group of advocates for colonization. The Bartleson-Bidwell Group was among the first to use this route after leaving Fort Hall. This route branched off in Montana and Utah via the Bozeman and Mormon trails. An iconic Learning Company game named for this route often ends with the player dying of dysentery, a fate that befell many travelers that took this trail to the Willamette Valley. For ten points, name this trail that settlers used to reach the Pacific Northwest.",
      "answer": "Oregon Trail"
    },
    {
      "question": "An artist from this country was influenced by Marcel Duchamp to weld together 42 bicycle frames. That artist, who filmed the aftermath of a 2008 earthquake in this country, also exhibited one million handmade porcelain sunflower seeds in England’s Tate Modern gallery. For ten points, name this country where artist and political activist Ai Weiwei consulted on the design of a “bird’s nest” stadium built for this country’s 2008 Summer Olympics.",
      "answer": "People’s Republic of China or Zhongguo"
    },
    {
      "question": "This mentor of Phog Allen played center on the McGill University football team in the 1890s. Luther Gulick asked this man for advice on keeping members of the Springfield YMCA in shape; this man used a pair of peach baskets in his ensuing invented game. The University of Kansas’ only losing coach in one sport is, ironically, this man. The NBA Hall of Fame is named after, for ten points, what inventor of basketball?",
      "answer": "James Naismith"
    },
    {
      "question": "During this conflict, Isaac Komnenos was ousted as ruler of Cyprus. Prior to this conflict, Guy of Lusignan’s [ghee of loo-sin-yon’s] Kingdom of Jerusalem was defeated by the Ayyubid Dynasty at the Battle of Hattin; Guy later led this conflict’s Siege of Acre [AH-kur]. While traveling during this conflict, Frederick Barbarossa drowned in the Saleph River. The Battle of Jaffa ended, for ten points, what crusade that ended in 1192 when Richard the Lionheart defeated Saladin?",
      "answer": "Third Crusade"
    },
    {
      "question": "This conflict featured an Italian naval intervention that was thwarted at Lissa in the first sea battle between ironclad fleets. Albrecht von Roon opened the draft to all male citizens prior to this conflict, which broke out after one side violated the Gastein Convention. This conflict was decided at the battle of Sadowa, which allowed the winners to take control of Schleswig and Holstein. For ten points, name this 1866 war in which Prussia defeated Austria within two months.",
      "answer": "Seven Weeks’ War War"
    },
    {
      "question": "In the alleged first game of this sport, one team dressed in handkerchiefs and turbans to distinguish themselves from the other team, and Rutgers beat Princeton 6 to 4. Lorin Deland invented this sport’s “flying wedge” play, which was banned in 1894. In 1905, Teddy Roosevelt invited leaders of this sport to the White House to discuss its poor safety record; shortly after, rules changes supported by John Heisman made the forward pass legal. For ten points, name this sport in which teams once earned four points for a touchdown.",
      "answer": "American football"
    },
    {
      "question": "In one game in this series, the American government uses the Bay of Pigs invasion as an alibi for a cosmonaut’s injuries sustained during Project Mercury. The end of the Cuban Missile Crisis thwarts the attempted defection of Nikolai Sokolov in this series. The Outer Heaven mercenary company, owned by Ocelot, grows strong enough to challenge world governments in this series’ fourth installment, “The Guns of the Patriots.” Hideo Kojima created, for ten points, what iconic stealth video game franchise whose protagonist is Solid Snake?",
      "answer": "Metal Gear"
    },
    {
      "question": "Nazi playwright Dietrich Eckart’s racist adaptation of this play depicts the Great Boyg and the Green-Clad Woman as Jews who are shamed and outsmarted by the title, Germanic character. In this play, Helga receives a silver button as a gift to her sister, Solveig, This play’s incidental music, including the songs “Morning Mood” and “The Death of Ase” was written by Edvard Grieg. For ten points, name this play written by Henrik Ibsen about a title Norwegian hero.",
      "answer": "Peer Gynt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Jamala won this event in 2016 by protesting the treatment of the Crimean Tatars in 1944. This event’s scoring reform in 2016 allowed participating countries to score twice as many “douze points” [dooz pwant] as before. This event was created in 1956 as an effort to popularize live TV throughout Western Europe. Australia is a guest competitor in, for ten points, what annual international song competition that was won in 2019 by the Netherlands?",
      "answer": "Eurovision Song Contest"
    },
    {
      "question": "During this conflict, suspected collaborators were tortured in the Phoenix Program. The Siege of Khe Sanh took place in this conflict after it was widened following a phantom attack on the USS Maddox in the Gulf of Tonkin. American troops in this conflict were criticized for their use of Agent Orange. For ten points, name this unpopular Southeast Asian war that ended with the capture of Saigon.",
      "answer": "Vietnam War"
    },
    {
      "question": "During a siege in this conflict, the victorious commander allegedly remarked “we have passed” in response to a speech by Dolores Ibarruri. A so-called Fifth Column of sympathetic civilians aided attackers during a battle won by Emile Mola in this war. The Carlists and Falangists were united during this conflict to defeat the Republicans. Francisco Franco won, for ten points, what conflict that included the Siege of Madrid?",
      "answer": "Spanish Civil War"
    },
    {
      "question": "A genre of music developed in this city was originally called “la-la” and was pioneered by Clifton Chenier, “The King of Zydeco.” A band leader from this city headed the Red Hot Peppers and composed the “King Porter Stomp.” The Original Dixieland Jass Band pioneered traditional jazz in this city, which was also home to a trumpeter who recorded “West End Blues” and “What a Wonderful World.” “Jelly Roll” Morton and Louis Armstrong hailed from, for ten points, what city where musicians parade down Bourbon Street during Mardi Gras?",
      "answer": "New Orleans"
    },
    {
      "question": "This event was a consolation choice after proposals for it to be held at Egyptian pyramids, a Roman amphitheater in Tunisia at sunrise, or a cruise ship fell through. Michael Lindsay-Hogg filmed this event, which took place at 3 Savile Row and featured Billy Preston. This event, which included multiple takes of “Don’t Let Me Down” and “Get Back,” was interrupted by police responding to noise complaints. The album Let It Be features songs recorded during, for ten points, what impromptu January 1969 event above London, the last time the Fab Four played live?",
      "answer": "the Beatles” rooftop concert"
    },
    {
      "question": "In the prelude to this conflict, Jeffery Amherst heavily restricted the use of gunpowder. The Conestoga Massacre was carried out by the Paxton Boys in the aftermath of this conflict. Appalled by colonial behavior during this conflict, George III passed a law banning settlers from moving past the Appalachian Mountains. The Royal Proclamation of 1763 was passed in response to, for ten points, what rebellion led by a namesake Ottawa Chief?",
      "answer": "Pontiac’s Rebellion"
    },
    {
      "question": "Dwight Evans spent all but one year of his career with this team, which fielded three generations of Hall of Fame left fielders in Jim Rice, Carl Yastrzemski, and “The Kid.” Pedro Martinez moved to this team from the Montreal Expos and helped the team end its championship drought of 86 years, allegedly caused by the team’s sale of Babe Ruth to a certain rival team based in New York. For ten points, name this Major League baseball team that plays its home games in Fenway Park.",
      "answer": "Boston Red Sox T"
    },
    {
      "question": "On April 13, 2016, this player went 22 for 50 from the field, scoring 60 points against the Utah Jazz to end the worst season in franchise history and his career. This man, who won an Oscar in 2018 for Best Animated Short Film for Dear Basketball, scored 81 points against the Raptors in 2006. For ten points, name this shooting guard who won five NBA titles with the Los Angeles Lakers in the early 2000s.",
      "answer": "Kobe Bryant"
    },
    {
      "question": "This musician worked with guitarist John McLaughlin on In a Silent Way, perhaps the most influential fusion album of the 1960s. The second movement of Concierto de Aranjuez was adapted in this man’s album Sketches of Spain. He pioneered cool jazz with the album The Birth of the Cool, and a 1959 album by him opens with the track “So What.” For ten points, name this influential jazz trumpeter behind Kind of Blue and Milestones. R",
      "answer": "Miles Davis"
    },
    {
      "question": "Kate Smith debuted a modified version of this song during the 1938 Armistice Day broadcast of her radio show. To avoid political undertones, this song’s lyrics “to the right” were changed to “through the night.” Woody Guthrie wrote “This Land Is Your Land” in direct response to this song that describes a light shining “from the mountains, to the prairies.” This song urges the listener to “stand beside” and “guide” the central land. Ending by calling the title country “My home sweet home,” For ten points, name this patriotic song by Irving Berlin.",
      "answer": "“God Bless America” T"
    },
    {
      "question": "One poem focusing on this conflict describes how “leaves / Flying, plunge and expire” and how the cenRtral figures “feed the grass row after rich row.” In another poem about this conflict, Robert Lowell described a monument near the “Old South Boston Aquarium” dedicated to a hero of this conflict named Robert Gould Shaw who led the siege of Fort Wagner in South Carolina. For ten points, name this war that was the subject of Allen Tate’s “Ode to the Confederate Dead.”",
      "answer": "U.S. Civil War"
    },
    {
      "question": "In one event featuring this sport in Auckland, bombs made of flour were thrown on teams and police beat clowns. A tour of one team in this sport was opposed by the Gleneagles Agreement and the group Halt All Racist Tours, owing to racial discrimination in the country from which the team came. Francois Pienaar led South Africa to win this sport’s 1995 World Cup. The Springboks and All Blacks are teams that play, for ten points, what form of football popular in Commonwealth nations?",
      "answer": [
        "Rugby Union",
        "Rugby league,"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This musician, who embarked on the Never Ending Tourin1988,releasedthe1979 album Slow Train Coming following his conversion to Evangelical Christianity. This artist included \"A Hard Rain's a-Gonna Fall\" on his seminal album titled The Freewheelin' [this artist]. The author of such folk hits as \"The Times They Are a-Changin'\"and\"Blowin'inthe Wind,\" for ten points, who is this winner of the 2016 Nobel Prize in Literature?",
      "answer": [
        "BobDylan",
        "RobertDylan",
        "RobertAllenZimmerman 2021-22 C Set History"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "A 1942 movie musical titled for this song follows the life of George M. Cohan. The Marquis de Lafayette’s band played this song as the British surrendered at Yorktown. In this song, the title character and his father “went down to Camp” with Captain Gooding and saw “men and boys / As thick as hasty pudding.” For ten points, name this song about an American who “stuck a feather in his cap / And called it macaroni.”",
      "answer": [
        "“Yankee Doodle”",
        "\"Yankee Doodle Dandy\""
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This actress gave a four-day tour duringtheKoreanWarcalled\"AnythingGoes.\"The nation of Egypt unilaterally banned this actress's films due to her conversion to Judaism following her marriage to Arthur Miller. At Madison Square Garden, this actress performed \"Happy Birthday, Mr. President\" for then headofstateJohnF.Kennedy.ThefilmSomeLikeit Hotfeatures, for ten points, which cultural iconand actress from the mid-20th century?",
      "answer": [
        "MarilynMonroe",
        "Norma JeaneMortenson",
        "or Norma JeaneBaker 2021-22 C Set History"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This man condemned commercial dishonesty in Boston in his sermon Theopolis Americana. This minister wrote to the judge William Stoughton [[\"STOW\"-ten]] to congratulate him on the destruction of \"devilism\" during the Salem Witch Trials. This religious figure's father, Increase, served as president of Harvard in the late17thcentury.A contemporary of Jonathan Edwards, for ten points, who was this prominent New England Puritan during the First Great Awakening? ANSWER:CottonMather(prompt on \"Mather\") (10) This man credits his relative lack of injury during his playing career to training in aikido withactorBruceLee.Thisbasketballplayerparticipatedinthe\"GameoftheCentury\" under coach John Wooden, being held to 15 points, in part due to a scratched cornea. This athlete, whopioneeredthe\"Skyhook\"technique,boycottedthe1968OlympicGamesshortly after his conversion to Islam. For ten points, name this Milwaukee Bucks and Los Angeles Lakers legend, a Hall of Fame Center.",
      "answer": [
        "KareemAbdul-Jabbar",
        "Ferdinand Lewis\"Lew\"Alcindor, Jr. 2021-22 C Set History"
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In the 1950s, this team was led by quarterback Y.A. Tittle and the \"Million Dollar Backfield.\"\nThis team's receiver Dwight Clark made \"The Catch\" in 1982, and in January 1995, with\nquarterback Steve Young, they became the first NFL team to win a fifth Super Bowl. For 10\npoints, name this team that won four titles under the leadership of Joe Montana.",
        "answer": "San Francisco 49ers, San Francisco, 49ers"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In the 1950s, this team was led by quarterback Y.A. Tittle and the \"Million Dollar Backfield.\"\nThis team's receiver Dwight Clark made \"The Catch\" in 1982, and in January 1995, with\nquarterback Steve Young, they became the first NFL team to win a fifth Super Bowl. For 10\npoints, name this team that won four titles under the leadership of Joe Montana.",
        "answer": "Jerry Rice, Rice"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Eddie Collins achieved this stat six times in a game on two separate occasions in September\n1912. In 1962, Maury Wills became the first modern player to achieve this feat a hundred times\nin a season, and Lou Brock once broke Ty Cobb’s record for this statistic. For 10 points, name\nthis baseball achievement whose records are now held by speedster Rickey Henderson.",
        "answer": [
          "stolen bases",
          "steals"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Henderson achieved the single-season and career stolen base records while playing for\nwhat team, which won the 1989 \"Earthquake Series\" against its cross-bay rivals?",
        "answer": [
          "Oakland Athletics",
          "Oakland",
          "Athletics",
          "A's"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This team’s best defensive player of the 1970s missed the entire 1979 season in favor of\nprofessional boxing. This team, which employed Ed “Too Tall” Jones, defeated the Dolphins and\nBroncos to win two 1970s Super Bowls, and lost two more appearances, both to the Steelers. For\n10 points, name this team of quarterback Roger Staubach and coach Tom Landry.",
        "answer": [
          "Dallas Cowboys",
          "Dallas",
          "Cowboys"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Who was the quarterback for all three of the Cowboys 1990s Super Bowl wins?",
        "answer": [
          "Troy Aikman",
          "Aikman"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The Bally and Williams corporations grew by manufacturing units for this game. Montague\nRedgrave patented the spring launcher central to this game in 1871, and in 1950, David Gottlieb\ncreated its modern form by adjusting the position of the controllable flippers. For 10 points,\nidentify this arcade game, in which points are scored for keeping the metal balls in play.",
        "answer": "pinball"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "What band, which described a \"deaf, dumb, and blind\" \"Pinball Wizard\" in their rock\nopera Tommy, also recorded \"My Generation\" and \"Baba O'Reilly?\"",
        "answer": "The Who"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This country featured the highest scorer at the inaugural FIFA World Cup, Guillermo Stabile, whose\nteam lost to Uruguay in the finals. Mario Kempes led this country to a 1978 World Cup win as the host\nnation. In this country’s win over England at the 1986 World Cup, the “Hand of God” scored one goal\nfor Diego Maradona. For ten points, name this country whose soccer team, led by Lionel Messi, placed\nsecond in the 2014 World Cup.",
        "answer": "Argentina"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In 2014, Messi won this award given to the World Cup’s best player. An annual award of the\nsame name is given by FIFA to the world’s best player.",
        "answer": [
          "Golden Ball",
          "Ballon d’Or"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Richard Jewell was falsely labelled a suspect for a crime committed during one of these events. At\nanother of these events, John Carlos and Tommie Smith were accused of doing a “Black Power” salute\nin Mexico City during the Star Spangled Banner while they stood on the medals podium. Atlanta’s\nCentennial Park was bombed in 1996 during, for ten points, what quadrennial sporting event boycotted\nby the Americans and Soviets in 1980 and 1984, respectively?",
        "answer": [
          "Summer Olympic Games",
          "Olympics"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Smith and Carlos took first and third in the 200 meter event in this sport. Justin Gatlin’s 2006\nrecord in the 100 meter event, at 9.766 seconds, was rescinded after a doping scandal.",
        "answer": [
          "track",
          "track and field",
          "sprinting",
          "sprint",
          "run",
          "running"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This university hosted the 1942 Rose Bowl after large outdoor gatherings during wartime were banned\non the west coast. It won one national championship when Gordon Hayward’s half court shot barely\nmissed. The “air ball” taunt was popularized by fans of this university’s basketball team, who camp\noutside Cameron Indoor Stadium in a tent complex named for its head coach. For ten points, name this university in Durham, North Carolina, which has won five men’s\nbasketball titles under Mike Krzyzewski [sha-SHEF-ski].",
        "answer": [
          "Duke University",
          "Duke"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In the 1992 NCAA Men’s Basketball championship game, Duke defeated this Big Ten state\nschool’s “Fab Five,” including Jalen Rose, who later claimed that Duke only recruited black players who\nwould be “Uncle Toms.”",
        "answer": [
          "University of Michigan",
          "Michigan"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The winning side of this match lit the cauldron in the opening ceremony of the 2002 Olympic Games.\nMarc Johnson tied this match, causing the other side to pull Vladislav Tretiak, its goalkeeper, after the\nfirst period. This game earned its name from a question asked by announcer Al Michaels in its final\nseconds. The winner of this match went on to defeat Finland to clinch the gold medal. For ten points,\nname this 1980 event in which the underdog United States defeated the Soviet Union in ice hockey at the\nOlympics.",
        "answer": "the Miracle on Ice,"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "When this sports magazine reported on the Miracle on Ice, its cover famously provided no\nheadline or explanation because, as the photographer noted, “everyone in America knew what happened.”",
        "answer": "Sports Illustrated"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "At this venue on New Years Eve 1989, David Hasselhoff performed his hit song Looking for Freedom.\nThis location was home to My God, Help Me To Survive This Deadly Love, a depiction of Brezhnev and\nHonecker embracing, in its East Side Gallery. Due to poor grammar, John F. Kennedy awkwardly claimed\nto be a donut after this structure was built, and Ronald Reagan appealed to “Mr. Gorbachev” to tear it\ndown. For ten points, name this structure that fell in 1989, reuniting the German capital city.",
        "answer": [
          "Berlin Wall",
          "Berliner Mauer"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This late British rock musician said “We send our wishes to all our friends who are on the other\nside of the wall” when performing his song Heroes at the Berlin Wall in 1987.",
        "answer": [
          "David Bowie",
          "Bowie",
          "David Robert Jones",
          "Jones"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man, while employed by his mentor Frankie Yale, was wounded by Frank Gallucio, a man who later served as his bodyguard. A group that investigated this man was chosen to be incorruptible by Eliot Ness; that group was disbanded after this man was arrested for tax evasion. Bugs Moran’s men were killed in the St. Valentine’s Day Massacre on the probable orders of, for ten points, what Chicago mobster nicknamed “Scarface?”",
        "answer": "Alphonse “Al” Capone"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Eliot Ness’ group of incorruptible agents that investigated Capone was given this nickname. Ness’ memoirs and their ensuing film and TV adaptations took this name.",
        "answer": "The Untouchables"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This team was on the losing end of Don Larsen’s World Series perfect game in 1956. In that year and seven others, this team lost to the Yankees in the World Series, though they won the 1955 World Series behind Duke Snider, Roy Campanella, rookie Sandy Koufax, and an infielder signed by Branch Rickey in 1947. For ten points, name this Major League Baseball team that moved to southern California in 1957 and broke the color barrier by signing Jackie Robinson to play in Brooklyn.",
        "answer": [
          "Brooklyn Dodgers",
          "Los Angeles Dodgers after “seven others” is read",
          "Brooklyn until it is read"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Larsen’s perfect game was described as “the biggest diamond in the biggest ring” by this broadcaster, who called that game and thousands of others during his 67-year career with the Dodgers. He retired in 2016.",
        "answer": "Vincent “Vin” Scully"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This band, whose members included Roger Taylor and John Deacon, negotiated with the East German government to use footage from Metropolis in the music video for “Radio Ga Ga.” Another song by this band includes the repeated cry “Bismillah!” and opens by asking “Is this the real life? Is this just fantasy?” In 1991, this band’s lead singer died 24 hours after announcing his battle with AIDS. For ten points, name this British rock band fronted by Freddie Mercury whose hits included “Bohemian Rhapsody” and “We Are the Champions.”",
        "answer": "Queen"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The female subject of Queen’s 1974 hit “Killer Queen” is described as “a built-in remedy/for” these two world leaders. One of these two men was killed in 1963; the other was deposed in 1964 and died of a heart attack in 1971.",
        "answer": [
          "Nikita Khrushchev and John F. Kennedy",
          "in either order",
          "prompt if only one is given. Note that “John” isn’t required as part of this answer - unlike most JFK questions - because the lyric is “for Khrushchev and Kennedy.”"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Francis M. Scala directed this group for over a decade and introduced one of its signature songs, which uses the “Gendarmes’ Duet,” an Offenbach melody. Thomas Jefferson gave a popular nickname to this group, whose leader wears a bearskin headpiece and carries a mace. John Philip Sousa once directed, for ten points, what military band that has played every inauguration since 1801 and is known as “The President’s Own?”",
        "answer": "United States Marine Band"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Gendarmes’ Duet melody is used for the Marines’ Hymn, which celebrates what September 1847 battle of the Mexican-American War with the line “From the halls of Montezuma?”",
        "answer": "Battle of Chapultepec"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In a movie set during this war, a man authorizes a pig farm as a site for his experiments to resurrect the extinct aurochs. Jessica Chastain portrayed Antonina in a 2017 movie set during this war, The Zookeeper’s Wife. In another movie set during this war, Liam Neeson played a businessman who establishes an enamel factory in Krakow and who saves 850 people by transporting them to his new munitions factory. For ten points, name this setting of Schindler’s List.",
        "answer": "World War II"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In Schindler’s List, this actor portrayed SS officer Amon G¨oth, who ran the Plaszow [plash-ov] concentration camp. His other historical roles include Charles Van Doren in Quiz Show, and his non- historical roles include Voldemort in the Harry Potter franchise.",
        "answer": "Ralph Fiennes , but be lenient"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "At the 1912 Olympics, this man was the U.S. representative in the first modern pentathlon. Joe Angelo saved this man’s life during his command at the Meuse-Argonne Offensive. George C. Scott won, but did not accept, an Oscar for portraying this man, who replaced Lloyd Fredendall after the Battle of Kasserine Pass and infamously slapped two shell-shocked soldiers in Sicily in 1943. For ten points, name this U.S. Army general, nicknamed “Old Blood and Guts,” who led the Third Army during the invasion of France.",
        "answer": "George S. Patton"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The film Patton was co-written by this man, who directed The Godfather and Apocalypse Now.",
        "answer": "Francis Ford Coppola"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "During this conflict, 16 inmates at Rawson Penitentiary were killed in the Trelew Massacre. A series of kidnappings during this conflict was called the Night of the Pencils. Near the end of this conflict, the National Reorganization Process seized control of the country. The Casa Rosada was bombed during this conflict as part as massive unrest in Buenos Aires. For ten points, name this 1974 to 1983 conflict between Marxist and Peronist factions in Argentina.",
        "answer": "Dirty War"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "During the Dirty War, grandmothers gathered in this main square in Buenos Aires to protest the disappearances of their relatives.",
        "answer": [
          "Plaza de Mayo",
          "May Square"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "During this conflict, the anarchist Nestor Mahkno seized control of an army due to a power vacuum caused by the fall of Hetman Skoropadsky’s government. Wrangel’s Fleet fled to occupied Constantinople at the end of the “southern” front of this conflict. American troops occupied Vladivostok during this conflict in support of Alexander Kolchak’s provisional government. For ten points, name this 1917 conflict between the Mensheviks and Bolsheviks for control of a European nation.",
        "answer": "Russian Civil War"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "During the Russian Civil War, a legion from this country captured an imperial gold reserve on the Trans-Siberian railway.",
        "answer": "Czechoslovakia"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A general from this dynasty was able to escape charges of treason by removing his shirt to reveal a tattoo reading “serve the country with the utmost loyalty.” This dynasty was founded by Yuanlang who led a coup d’etat against Emperor Gong. This dynasty, the first to use paper money, is broken into Northern and Southern periods. Kublai Khan conquered, for ten points, what Chinese dynasty succeeded by the Yuan?",
        "answer": "Song"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Yuan conquered the Song at this 1279 naval battle despite being outnumbered 10 to 1.",
        "answer": [
          "Battle of Yamen",
          "Naval Battle of Mount Ya"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The “Dope Sheet” was a press release that this NFL team’s co-founder wrote in its first few seasons. This team won the 1967 NFL Championship game, which had a game-time temperature of negative 15 degrees and was known as the “Ice Bowl.” This team anchors the smallest market for any team in the four major American sports leagues. Vince Lombardi coached, for ten points, what publicly-owned NFL team that plays its home games at Lambeau Field in Wisconsin?",
        "answer": [
          "Green Bay Packers",
          "either underlined portion"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Lambeau Field is the largest stadium in Wisconsin; the second largest is this stadium at the University of Wisconsin. This stadium is named for a Union training camp that, itself, was named after a Wisconsin governor.",
        "answer": "Camp Randall Stadium"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "An organization at this site was inspired by Henry Wisner to create a “Great Chain” designed by the Sterling Iron Works to impede enemy ships. ThatForganization at this location later began a tradition of training “the Long Grey Line.” Polish engineer Tadeusz Kosciuszko designed this site, the oldest continually held military garrison in the country. Benedict Arnold attempted to surrender this site to the British. For ten points, name this New York site where the United States Military Academy is located.",
        "answer": "West Point"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Once considered one of the finest college football programs, Army has produced three winners of the trophy given to the most outstanding NCAA football player but none since 1938. What is this trophy called? A",
        "answer": "Heisman Memorial Trophy"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "John the Blind of Bohemia fought in this war whose first naval engagement took place at Sluys [slois], and Edward the Black Prince’s reputation grew after his success at Najera in this conflict. The Treaty of Bretigny briefly halted this conflict that was depicted in Auguste Rodin’s The Burghers of Calais. The battle of Crecy during this conflict demonstrated the power of the longbow, as did the battle of Agincourt. For ten points, the siege of Orleans was lifted by Joan of Arc in what lengthy conflict between England andRFrance?",
        "answer": "Hundred Years’ War"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "One of the precursors to the Hundred Years’ War was an English claim to the French throne after the death of Charles IV and the end of this dynasty that had ruled France for more than 300 years after being started by Hugh in 987.",
        "answer": "Capetian D"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man was given a clock and the elephant Abul-Abbas after making contact with the Abbasid caliphate. The Treaty of Verdun divided the lands of this man between his sons, including his successor Louis the Pious. Basque troops ambushed this son of Pepin the Short in the Roncevaux Pass, an event related in The Song of Roland. For ten points, name this Frankish king who was crowned by Pope Leo III as the first Holy Roman Emperor.",
        "answer": [
          "Charlemagne",
          "Charles the Great",
          "Charles I BORNUS: Charlemagne was crowned on this day of the year. Other events in history on this day include Andrew Johnson’s pardoning of Confederate veterans, Washington crossing the Delaware, and, traditionally at least, the birth of a particularly influential religious leader. ANSWER: December 25",
          "Christmas 6 One song written during this decade includes the refrain “It ain’t me, it ain’t me, I ain’t no millionaire’s son.” Another song from this decade is narrated by man who claims he’s “got eyes like a bat, and feet are flat” before noting he’s “only eighteen, got a ruptured spleen” to his “Sarge.” D Another song from this decade includes the refrain “How many roads must a man walk down / Before you can call him a man?” “Draft Dodger Rag” was written near the end of, for ten points, what decade in which Bob Dylan performed at the March on Washington? ANSWER: 1960s"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In 2016, Bob Dylan became the only member of the Rock and Roll Hall of Fame to win this prestigious international award “for having created new poetic expressions within the great American song tradition.”",
        "answer": "Nobel Prize in Literature T"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In one of this actor’s films, Harlen Maguire is tasked with assassinating this actor’s character, Michael Sullivan, an Irish mobster in Depression-era Illinois. In another film, this man fires a pistol repeatedly at an approaching tank when the tank is suddenly bombed from above. This actor in the 2002 film Road to Perdition, commands the 2nd Ranger Battalion in a film which opens with the landing at Normandy. In F that film, this man play Captain John Miller, whose men are tasked with finding a missing paratrooper. For ten points, name this actor who starred in Saving Private Ryan.",
        "answer": "Tom Hanks"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In this 1995 film, Tom Hanks plays astronaut Jim Lovell who commanded the namesake mission that failed to land on the moon but successfully returned to earth.",
        "answer": "Apollo 13 A"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "During the 1964 World’s Fair, this man developed the “Great Moments with Mr. Lincoln” exhibit. D Charles Mintz took the rights for a character named “Lucky Rabbit” that was created by this man. Art Babbitt helped lead a 1941 strike against this man on charges of anti-Semitism that others roundly denounced. With Ub Iwerks, this man developed a character that debuted in Steamboat Wilie, and Nikita Khruschev was denied access to one of this man’s theme parks. For ten points, name this animator and business mogul who developed Mickey Mouse.",
        "answer": "Walter “Walt” Disney"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Though most Disney Studios films are fictional, they occasionally make films based on historic events, though often with many liberties taken, such as this 1995 film that included the characters John Smith and Chief Powhatan.",
        "answer": "Pocahontas T"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The \"Praises of Italy\" passage is found in a treatise concerning this subject written by Virgil known as the Georgics. Dactylic hexameter is used in another treatise on this subject by Hesiod [[HEH-see-ud]] known as Works and Days, imploring the reader to pray to Demeter. Cato the Elder describes the virtues of animal husbandry and plowing, both subsets of, for ten points, what discipline in his work, De Agricultura?",
        "answer": [
          "Farming",
          "Agriculture before \"de Agricultura\" is mentioned",
          "husbandry before mentioned"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Virgil also wrote about what Trojan prince who fled to mainland Italy and settled the region of Latium [[LAY-shee-um]]?",
        "answer": [
          "Aeneas ]",
          "The Aeneid"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Transfer of footballers within this entity was the subject of the 1995 Bosman ruling. This entity is derived from an earlier \"Coal and Steel Community\" and was formally established by the 1992 Maastricht Treaty. In 2016, the United Kingdom voted in a referendum to leave this body, an act known as \"Brexit.\" For ten points, name this political and economic association of countries from the namesake continent.",
        "answer": "European Union or EU"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The United Kingdom is so far the only state to leave the EU. Many states have made overtures toward joining, however, including this Yugoslav successor state that agreed to change its name in 2019 to avoid conflict with its southern neighbor Greece.",
        "answer": [
          "Republic of North Macedonia",
          "Macedonia",
          "Republika Severna Makedonija",
          "or Republika e Maqedonisë së Veriut"
        ]
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "THE COURT OF THE FRENCH KING",
      "prompt": "What important person in the reigns of the final four kings of pre-Revolutionary France was...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "A radical free speech advocate and the author of Candide?",
          "answer": [
            "Voltaire",
            "Francois-Marie Arouet",
            "Arouet"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "A finance minister whose cheapness caused his name to be applied to an all-black outline\nportrait?",
          "answer": [
            "Etienne de Silhouette",
            "Silhouette"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "The king from 1610 to 1643 who ended the regency of Marie de Medici?",
          "answer": "Louis XIII"
        },
        {
          "question": "The thinker who explained separation of powers in The Spirit of the Laws?",
          "answer": [
            "Baron Montesquieu",
            "Charles-Louis de Secondat",
            "Secondat"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "The Catholic \"Red Eminence\" who dominated the court in the 1620s and 30s?",
          "answer": [
            "Cardinal Richelieu",
            "Richelieu",
            "Armand Jean du Plessis",
            "du Plessis"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "The influential mistress of Louis XV with a flamboyant hairstyle?",
          "answer": [
            "Madame de Pompadour",
            "Pompadour"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "The formulator of the law of conservation of mass and the metric system who was executed by\nthe Revolution despite being the \"Father of Modern Chemistry?\"",
          "answer": [
            "Antoine Lavoisier",
            "Lavoisier"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "The composer of religious music for Louis XIV who died after shattering his foot with a\nbaton?",
          "answer": [
            "Jean-Baptiste Lully",
            "Lully"
          ]
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "BRITISH CELEBRITIES",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Is the longest-reigning monarch?",
          "answer": [
            "Queen Elizabeth II",
            "Elizabeth II"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the divorced wife of Prince Charles, who was killed in a 1997 car crash?",
          "answer": [
            "Diana",
            "Diana Spencer"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Is the Cambridge physicist who has studied black holes for decades despite suffering from ALS?",
          "answer": [
            "Stephen Hawking",
            "Hawking"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Is the retired Manchester United midfielder and national team captain known for “bending” his free\nkicks?",
          "answer": [
            "David Beckham",
            "Beckham"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the frontman and writer of “Bohemian Rhapsody” for Queen?",
          "answer": [
            "Freddie Mercury",
            "Mercury"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the silent film star who directed and starred in The Great Dictator?",
          "answer": [
            "Sir Charlie Chaplin",
            "Chaplin",
            "Charlie Chaplin"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Was praised for his leadership during the failed 1914 Endurance expedition?",
          "answer": [
            "Sir Ernest Shackleton",
            "Shackleton"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Is the naturalist producer and narrator of Life on Earth and brother of actor Richard?",
          "answer": [
            "Sir David Attenborough",
            "David Attenborough",
            "Attenborough"
          ]
        }
      ],
      "prompt": "Who..."
    },
    {
      "category": "Prohibition in the United States",
      "prompt": "Concerning the period of Prohibition in U.S. history, name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "\"Public Enemy Number One\" whose gang perpetrated the St. Valentine's Day Massacre.",
          "answer": "AlCaponeor Alphonse GabrielCapone"
        },
        {
          "question": "Nickname for Eliot Ness's \"incorruptible\" enforcers.",
          "answer": "TheUntouchables"
        },
        {
          "question": "Evangelist and former baseball player who claimed Prohibition would end all crime.",
          "answer": "BillySundayor Billy AshleySunday 2021-22 C Set History"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) During this era, Josquin des Prez (pr. JOHS-kin day PRAY) made advances in polyphony (puh-LIFF-uh-nee), and Giovanni da Palestrina wrote the (20 pts) ",
        "Pope Marcellus Mass. This era's music came under fire at the Council of Trent and was succeeded by the (10 pts) ",
        "Baroque period. For 10 points, identify this period in Western musical history in which motets and masses were the dominant form of music, and which shares its name with a \"rebirth\" in literature and visual arts."
      ],
      "answer": "the Renaissance"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Buffalo Springfield insisted that the song \"For What It's Worth\" was about the Sunset Strip curfew riots and not this event. This event was the subject of Country Joe and the Fish's biggest hit. A veteran of this conflict is the subject of (20 pts) ",
        "Bruce Springsteen's \"Born in the USA,\" and a (10 pts) ",
        "protest against this conflict inspired Neil Young to write \"Ohio\" about the Kent State shootings. For 10 points, name this war which inspired copious protest music in the late 1960s."
      ],
      "answer": "Vietnam War, Vietnam"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In a musical named for this dance, Judge Forestier (pr. for-ess-TEER) finally concludes\nthat \"It's All Right With Me.\" That Cole Porter musical discusses the scandal that this\ndance, which is in 2/4 time and based on the quadrille (pr. kwah-DREEL), caused when it was\nintroduced to (20 pts) ",
        "Paris in 1858. This dance first appeared in Jacques (10 pts) ",
        "Offenbach's Orpheus\nin the Underworld. For 10 points, name this characteristic French music hall dance involving\nwomen kicking their legs high."
      ],
      "answer": "the can-can"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A 2001 panel of experts in this sport named Regla Torres and Lorenzo Bernardi among\nits three best players of all time. William Morgan invented this game in 1895 as a less\nphysical use of (20 pts) ",
        "basketball courts. Al Scates is the most successful coach in this sport,\nand was the trainer of the generally regarded best-ever player at this sport, (10 pts) ",
        "Karch\nKiraly. For 10 points, name this game in which a libero, blockers, and setters play across an\nelevated net."
      ],
      "answer": "volleyball"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) One leader of this conflict, Jose Sanjurjo, died in a plane crash after leaving Estoril.\nThe term “Fifth Column” was coined during this war. The Abraham Lincoln Brigade was\none of the International Brigades to join this conflict, and (20 pts) ",
        "Nazi Germany supported\none side in this conflict with the Condor Legion. After seizing (10 pts) ",
        "Cartagena, Republican forces\nsurrendered to the Nationalists. For ten points, name this conflict in an Iberian country that brought\nFrancisco Franco to power."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Spanish Civil War",
        "Spanish Civil"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Livy claims that one participant in this conflict used heated vinegar to cross a blocked\nmountain pass. Quintus Fabius was nicknamed “the delayer” during this conflict for refusing\nto engage in battle. One side in this conflict lost at (20 pts) ",
        "Lake Trasimene [trah-sih-meh-nee]\nbut later won the decisive victory on the plains of Zama under Scipio [SKIP-ee-oh],\ncounteracting a devastating loss at Cannae [CANN-aye]. The (10 pts) ",
        "Alps were traversed by\nHannibal during, for ten points, what second of a series of conflicts between Rome and Carthage?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "2nd Punic War",
        "2nd Punic"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man threatened to kill Dennis Wilson, a Beach Boy, for changing the lyrics to his\nsong “Cease to Exist.” Vincent Bugliosi used circumstantial evidence to convict this man of\nconspiracy to (20 pts) ",
        "murder. He predicted a chaotic white vs. black war triggered by his music\nand that of the (10 pts) ",
        "Beatles; this man called that conflict Helter Skelter. For ten points, name this man\nwho, in 1969, ordered Sharon Tate and eight other people to be murdered by his so-called “Family.”"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Charles Manson",
        "Manson"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Competitive venues for this game, invented by Alfred Butts, will use molded plastic\ninstead of wood so that players can’t “braille.” The SOWPODS list is used in this game,\nwhose 2015 (20 pts) ",
        "French championship was won by Nigel Richards after just nine weeks of\npreparation. This game, an inspiration for (10 pts) ",
        "Words With Friends, uses strategies that involve\nthe Triple Word Score bonuses on corner tiles and “bingoes” for playing 7 tiles at once. For ten points,\nname this word spelling board game."
      ],
      "answer": "Scrabble"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This musician honored the first black heavyweight champion in his album A Tribute\nto Jack Johnson. He played flugelhorn in addition to his main instrument for a rendition\nof Rodrigo’s (20 pts) ",
        "Concierto de Aranjuez arranged by Gil Evans. This trumpeter added\nCannonball Adderly to his “first great quintet” and pioneered the genre of (10 pts) ",
        "cool jazz with\nalbums such as Sketches of Spain and songs like “Freddie Freeloader” and “So What”. For ten points,\nname this jazz trumpeter who recorded Kind of Blue."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Miles Davis",
        "Davis"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Description acceptable. In 2015, Marc Lasry and Wes Edens received $250 million in\npublic funds for one of these projects, months after the same amount was cut from the\nUniversity of Wisconsin budget by governor Scott Walker. In 2014, Stan (20 pts) ",
        "Kroenke\nbought 60 acres of land in California, threatening to use it for one of these projects if St.\nLouis refused to upgrade the Edward Jones (10 pts) ",
        "Dome. For ten points, name these controversial\nconstruction projects, often lobbied for by the owners of MLB, NBA, and NFL teams."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "building new professional sports facilities",
        "sports facilities",
        "sports stadium",
        "stadium",
        "arena"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) (TIEBREAKER EXAMPLE QUESTION) Despite the protests of the DNC, Lyndon Johnson snubbed this politician in\nfavor of Hubert Humphrey as his running mate. This politician rose to prominence (20 pts) ",
        "investigating mafia connections within worker unions, leading him into conflict\nwith the Teamsters and Jimmy Hoffa. Eugene McCarthy conceded (10 pts) ",
        "California to\nthis politician shortly before Sirhan Sirhan shot this man in 1968. For ten points, name this U.S.\nAttorney General and member of the Kennedy family."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Robert Francis Kennedy",
        "R Kennedy",
        "Bobby Kennedy",
        "RFK sr.",
        "RFK senior",
        "Robert Francis Kennedy Sr.",
        "Robert Francis Kennedy Senior"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In 1967, this man argued that “it’s [the media’s] responsibility for spreading” the news that he had taken LSD, denying he had “encouraged” his fans to take drugs. This man was arrested in Tokyo for possession of marijuana in 1980, canceling a (20 pts)",
        "Wings tour and ultimately causing the breakup of the band. Drug-inspired songs like “Got to Get You Into My Life,” and “Magical (10 pts)",
        "Mystery Tour” were sung by, for ten points, what British singer who co-wrote those songs with John Lennon in The Beatles?"
      ],
      "answer": "James Paul McCartney"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A team in this sport hired Kristi Toliver as an assistant coach; Toliver also plays for Washington’s professional women’s team in this sport, the Mystics. The first full-time (20 pts)",
        "female assistant coach in this sport’s top league was Becky Hammon, who was hired in 2014 as an assistant under (10 pts)",
        "Gregg Popovich. Breanna Stewart, Maya Moore, and Diana Taurasi were college stars at Connecticut in, for ten points, what sport whose women’s league was established in 1997, the same year that Michael Jordan won his fifth title in this sport for the Chicago Bulls?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "basketball",
        "NBA and/or WNBA"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Eighteen of these works, including ones “for France,” “for Freedom,” and for “Airmen,” were commissioned by Cincinnati’s Eugene Goossens in 1942 to recognize the war effort. A speech by Henry (20 pts)",
        "Wallace inspired another of these musical works for Goossens, which was composed by Aaron (10 pts)",
        "Copland and premiered at income tax time to honor its subject, the “Common Man.” For ten points, name this type of musical piece, a usually short flourish for brass and percussion, commonly associated with the entrance of a royal leader."
      ],
      "answer": "fanfares"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Although lawyers debated whether this man owned a rare pair of Bruno Magli shoes, a photograph that was published in the National Enquirer supposedly showing him wearing the shoes was not entered into evidence. This man, who was arrested after a (20 pts)",
        "sports memorabilia robbery at the Palace Station casino in Las Vegas, was defended by Johnnie (10 pts)",
        "Cochran and Robert Kardashian in an earlier trial concerning the deaths of Ron Goldman and Nicole Brown. For ten points, name this NFL running back who was acquitted of murder in a massive 1995 trial."
      ],
      "answer": "Orenthal James “OJ” Simpson"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This conflict prompted CIA chief John Stockwell to resign after foreign troops invaded Shaba. A minor player in this conflict was the FLEC, a front for the liberation of Cabinda. This conflict became known as (20 pts)",
        "“Cuba’s Vietnam” after the amount of aid that Fidel Castro sent to aid Agostinho Neto. This war finally ended when Jonas Savimbi was killed in (10 pts)",
        "2002, ending 27 years of fighting that began when Portugal granted the country independence. The UNITA and MPLA factions fought in, for ten points, what civil war in southern Africa?"
      ],
      "answer": "Angolan Civil War"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This activity was banned at the Russian Antarctic stations in 1959 after a frustrated scientist killed his opponent with an ax. Both Napoleon and Benjamin Franklin were beaten by “The Turk,” a (20 pts)",
        "hoax automaton that played this game. Komodo and Stockfish are modern computer programs that improved on the AI system (10 pts)",
        "Deep Blue, which defeated Garry Kasparov at this game in 1997. Magnus Carlsen is the current world champion of, for ten points, what centuries-old board game involving knights and rooks?"
      ],
      "answer": "chess"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Michael Jordan played for this team’s AA affiliate, the Birmingham Barons, during his first retirement from basketball. Steve Dahl promoted and executed “Disco Demolition Night” at this team’s (20 pts)",
        "Comiskey Park in 1979. Multiple members of this team, including Buck Weaver and Shoeless Joe Jackson, were (10 pts)",
        "accused of taking bribes to throw the 1919 World Series, after which it took until 2005 to win another World Series. For ten points, name this baseball team that experienced the “Black Sox” scandal."
      ],
      "answer": "Chicago White Sox"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In the prelude to this conflict, Lord Dalhousie flared tensions by annexing land under the Doctrine of Lapse. Soldiers in this conflict were shot out of cannons during particularly vicious fighting at (20 pts)",
        "Cawnpore. Lucknow was besieged at the start of this conflict. This conflict was sparked after new (10 pts)",
        "cartridges for the Enfield rifle were allegedly greased with fat to offend both Muslim and Hindus soldiers. The British Raj was established in the aftermath of, for ten points, what 1857 revolt in India?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Sepoy Mutiny",
        "Indian Revolt of 1857 before “India” is read"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The first battle in this conflict arose after merchants aboard the Thomas Coutts signed a trade bond despite orders to the contrary, prompting the (20 pts)",
        "Hyacinth and Volage to blockade a nearby town. During this war, a letter asking “where is your conscience” was addressed to one side’s monarch by Lin (10 pts)",
        "Zexu. This conflict ended in the Treaty of Nanking which ceded Hong Kong to Great Britain. The Qing were defeated in, for ten points, what 1839 war over the trade of a namesake drug."
      ],
      "answer": "First Opium War"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) While visiting Germany, this man once got so drunk that he started conducting a A celebratory band and blowing kisses to the crowd. This man’s vice president once referred to his reforms as “economic genocide.” Jesse Helms asked this man about the potential whereabouts of (20 pts)",
        "Larry MacDonald after an aerial incident under this man’s predecessor. This man, who released the KAL 007 black box, once stood in front of a (10 pts)",
        "tank to thwart a coup against his predecessor. For ten points, name this man who became the first president of Russia in 1991."
      ],
      "answer": "Boris Yeltsin 3RIn a 2006 game against the Toronto Raptors, this man scored the second most points ever in a single game with 81. In 2018, this man became the first African-American to win the Academy Award for Best Animated Short Film for Dear + Basketball. Despite disagreements with teammate Shaquille O’Neal, this man won three NBA championships in a row from 2000 to 2002 and five in his career and became known as “The * Black Mamba.” For ten points, name this Los Angeles Laker who was killed in a helicopter crash in January, 2020. ANSWER: Kobe Bryant D"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The second of these conflicts featured Barcids fighting on three fronts, including two sons of Hamilcar. The loser of the third of these conflicts was raided by (20 pts)",
        "Numidians and fell after a three-year siege under Scipio Aemilianus. The second of these conflicts was a sixteen year long campaign that ended at the Battle of Zama. Cato the Elder ended every speech advocating for the destruction of (10 pts)",
        "Rome’s enemy in these wars. For ten points, name this series of wars between Rome and Carthage."
      ],
      "answer": "Punic Wars T"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In this film, Arthur Parsons claims that investors are worried that the protagonist “doResn’t have the resolve to make the tough choices.” In this film, playwright Tracy Letts plays the protagonist’s advisor Fritz Beebe. In this film, (20 pts)",
        "RAND Corporation employee Daniel Ellsberg makes photocopies of a set of documents that cause him to confirm that Robert McNamara had lied to him. Editor-in-chief Ben (10 pts)",
        "Bradlee helps convince Kathy Graham to go through with the publication of the Pentagon Papers in, for ten points, what film starring Meryl Streep, that focuses on a D.C. newspaper?"
      ],
      "answer": "The Post D"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "One group who performed this art form premiered their first piece, Le Pavillon d'Armide [[luh pah-vee-YOHN dar-MEED]], in Paris in 1909, following it up with Prince Igor, both of which were choreographed by Michel Fokine [[mee-SHEL foh- KEEN]]. (*) Sergei Diaghilev [[de-AH-guh-lef]] founded an influential Russian company known for this art form, music for which included The Firebird and The Rite of Spring by Igor (*) Stravinsky. For ten points, name this art form of performative dance, practiced by Anna Pavlova and Vaslav Nijinsky."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Ballet",
        "Ballet Russes"
      ]
    }
  ]
}